RG 118, Veteran Association of the Hartford City Guard, 1867-1917
Connecticut State Library
Veteran Association of the Hartford City Guard records
1861-1925
Connecticut State Library
Veteran Association of the Hartford City Guard
2 cubic feet
The Veteran Association of the Hartford City Guard was organized on November 26, 1867. It was composed of those persons who were active or honorary members of the Hartford City Guard prior to July 5, 1865. The Association’s main objective was social with the intention “to keep alive old and pleasant memories and perpetuation of recollections of the old Company.” Each year they held a reunion on the second Wednesday of January. The first reunion was held on January 8, 1868. At their 50th reunion held in 1917, it was agreed that it should be the last reunion.
RG118
1917-001
Historical Note
The Veteran Association of the Hartford City Guard was organized on November 26, 1867. It was composed of those persons who were active or honorary members of Hartford City Guard prior to July 5, 1865. Its object was social and to keep alive old and pleasant memories and perpetuation of recollections of the old Company. Each year they held a reunion on the 2nd Wednesday in January. The first one was held on January 8, 1868. At their 50th reunion held on January 10, 1917, it was agreed that it should be the last reunion.
Scope and Content
The material, dated 1861-1917, consists of the constitution; registers and rolls; reports and histories; correspondence; orders; treasurer's reports and receipted bills; menus, invitations and programs; clippings; photographs; printing blocks; and ribbons and badges. There are also copies of the Constitution and By-Laws and the Original Roll of the Hartford City Guard, 1861, and the Charter and By-Laws of the Veteran City Guard, 1886.
Separated Material
Association artifacts were transferred to the Museum of Connecticut History. This collection included seven U.S. naval and regimental flags; one Connecticut 1st National Guard bandsman's hat; a mechanical adding device; assorted medals and insignia and a collection of rubber stamps.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Veteran Association of the Hartford City Guard
Subjects:
Veteran Association of the Hartford City Guard -- Records and correspondence; Clubs -- Connecticut -- Hartford
Document Types:
Bylaws (administrative records); Constitutions; Correspondence; Financial records; Invitations; Membership lists; Programs; Reports; Minutes
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Provenance
At their 50th reunion held on January 10, 1917, it was agreed that it should be the last reunion, and Secretary Hitchcock was requested to deposit in the State Library the records of the organization. He died on November 18, 1917. A letter to Ward W. Jacobs, Treasurer, dated November 24, 1917, from George S. Godard, State Librarian, states that Major Hitchcock did bring the chest with some of the records to the State Library.
A Connecticut State Library internal letter dated October 6, 1924 states W.S. Jacobs brought additional material that was added to the original accession.
Container List
- Records, 1861-1917
  - 1. Constitution and by-laws of the Hartford City Guard, 1861 (Box 1)
  - 2. Original roll of the Company, 1861 May 1 (Box 1)
  - 3. Constitution of the Veterans Association of the Hartford City Guard (V.A.H.C.G.), Hartford, Conn., 1867 (Box 1)
    Extra copies of this Constitution are in Box 2.
  - 4. City register, 1880 January 1 (Box 1)
    Compiled from the records of the Hartford City Guard.
  - 5. Catalogue of the members of the V.A.H.C.G., 1885-1886 (Box 1)
  - 6. Charter and by-laws of the Veteran City Guard of Hartford, 1886 (Box 1)
    Organized March 13, 1878. Reorganized March 11, 1885.
  - 7. Report of the proceedings of the V.A.H.C.G. at 25th Anniversary, 19th Reunion, 1886 January 13 (Box 1)
  - 8. Annual reunion 1887 (20th Reunion of V.A.H.C.G.), Officers for 1887-1888 (Box 1)
  - 9. Catalogue of members of the V.A.H.C.G., Hartford, Conn., 1891 (Box 1)
    Extra copies of this are in Box 2.
  - 10. Address of welcome by the President, 1893 (Box 1)
  - 11. Club house material, 1908 (Box 1)
  - 12. 50th Anniversary, 44th Reunion dinner of V.A.H.C.G., 1911 January 11 (Box 1)
  - 13. 49th Reunion, 1916 January 12 (Box 1)
  - 14. 50th Reunion, 1917 January 10 (Box 1)
  - 15. Members of the V.A.H.C.G. with last known address, 1917 January 1 (Box 1)
  - 16. Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1882-1922 (Box 1)
    - Regrets, 1894 (Box 1)
    - Letters regarding death of Major Henry P. Hitchcock on Sunday, November 18, 1917 (Box 1)
  - 17. General orders, Headquarters, Veteran City Guard Battalion, 1887, 1892, 1905, 1908, 1909, 1911 (Box 1)
  - 18. History (Box 1)
    - History by Maj. B. F. Blakeslee, 1884 (Box 1)
    - History by James Smith (20th Reunion), 1887 January 12 (Box 1)
    - History read at 36th Annual Reunion and Dinner of V.A.H.C.G., January 14, 1903, by Charles H. Parsons (Box 1)
  - 19. Secretary's reports (Box 1)
    - 1875 January 13 (Box 1)
    - 1877 January 10 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1877 January 10 (Box 1)
  - 20. Treasurer's account, 1868-1917; 1 volume (Box 1)
  - 21. Treasurer's reports and receipted bills, 1868-1916 (Box 1)
    - Receipts only, 1868 (Box 1)
    - Receipts only, 1874 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer's report & receipted bills, 1875 (Box 1)
    - Receipted bills, 1876-1879 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer reports & receipted bills, 1880-1885 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer reports & receipted bills, 1886-1889, 1891 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer reports & receipted bills, 1896-1898 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer reports & receipted bills, 1907-1908, 1910-1912, 1914-1916 (Box 1)
  - 22. Songs and poems (Box 1)
  - 23. Sample envelopes (Box 1)
  - 24. Menus, invitations, programs. First Annual Dinner through 50th Reunion, 1868-1917 (Box 1)
    The First Annual Dinner was held January 8, 1868 and the 50th Annual Dinner was held January 10, 1917. There are no items for the 5th, 7th, 8th, 9th, and 11th Annual Dinners. There are invitations only for the 47th, 48th and 50th Annual Dinners.
  - 24-A. Invitation letters, 23rd Annual Dinner, 27th through 29th, 31st through 50th., 1890-1917 (Box 1)
  - 24-B. Miscellaneous invitations, 1902-1916 (Box 1)
  - 25. Catalogue - Veteran City Guard Art Loan Exhibition, 1884 (Box 1)
  - 26. Orders No. 1, 1910 March 21 (Box 1)
    Regarding appointments and non-commissioned staff.
  - 27. Rules for Sergeant of the Guard and clipping (August 25, 1862) giving Hartford City Guard Officers (Box 1)
  - 28. Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Calendars, 1909, 1911 (Box 1)
    - Pamphlets, 1915, 1925 (Box 1)
  - 29. Printing blocks, 1 envelope (Box 2)
  - 30. Photographs, 1 envelope (Box 2)
    Some are identified on back and some are not.
  - 31. Ribbons, badges, etc., 1 envelope (Box 2)
  - 32. Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Includes Major Hitchcock's obituary.
  - 33. Hartford Courant, 1917 November 19 (Box 2)
    Page 11 contains obituary of Major Hitchcock.
  - 34. Hartford Times, 1917 November 19 (Box 2)
    Page 17 contains obituary of Major Hitchcock.
  - Extra copies of items 3 and 9 from Box 1. (Box 2)